Rainor [music] Pope is the co-founder
and CEO of Matt X. He's a former math
wiz and hasll programmer who became a
TPU architect for Google and now he's
teamed up with Google's [music] former
chief chip architect to design a better
chip for AI.
So a year ago everyone was saying Google
is canled.
>> You know AI is going to eat their
search. No one's going to search for
things and therefore the business um you
know won't do well. Obviously that
sentiment has really shifted in part
helped by uh you know Gemini 3 is really
good and then also it's really fast you
know it's powered by the the custom chip
hardware Google has
>> you were inside Google for actually I
think a lot of the foundational period
>> uh laying the groundwork for that stuff
what do people not appreciate about what
Google did right to lay all the
groundwork for their current AI success
>> they started with the research right the
transformers came from there pretty
uh anyone who's maybe I don't know over
30 and at a large lab has been at Google
brain at some point. Um so uh I think
there's just like there was and has been
a lot of talent there. TPUs are are
pretty good. Um uh I mean we think
there's better you can do of course but
they at least had the option like the
opportunity to design the TPUs for um
for neural nets at least rather than
graphics applications like Nvidia. Um
and so the the overall architecture
starting with single core doing what was
at the time reasonably large systolic
arrays by today's standards nowhere near
as much but um I I think those were a
lot of like really good decisions.
>> When did the TPU project start?
>> TPU v1 was announced in 2016 I think. Um
that was what actually kind of led to
the creation of uh all of those 2016
2017 startups. So Sirius Grock,
Graphcore, Samanova all of those. TPOV1
actually was I think is a really
impressive project. It was uh done on a
very short timeline maybe I don't know
the full details but maybe about a year
or so maybe a year and a half um with a
skeleton team of uh 20 30 people um
really really minimal viable project
product more recent TPUs and more recent
AI chips in general like can't do that
because the market has moved and the and
the uh stakes um or the table stakes are
much higher but um the first generation
product they just one big systolic array
um stick a memory next to But we're done
and it was it was really simple. Uh a
nice nice elegant product.
>> And obviously that TPUv1 predates the
transformer. Is that just a coincidence
that they happened at very similar times
or
>> Yeah. Related in some way?
>> Yeah. I mean there was a period of maybe
about uh four years like um a lot of I
mean a lot of ML research or neural net
research prior to transformer. So uh
what was popular LSTMs uh and and
confidence and resception the big
thinking at the time was um uh was to
adapt it to be used for LSTMs um uh it's
a reasonable fit uh there but yeah no I
mean I think just there was just a huge
flurry of activity I think what like why
did it all happen then not later is
probably just because people stopped
publishing like in 2022
was about the time when just Google
completely stopped publishing it uh
research and so all the good papers are
from before that as a result.
>> Right. Right. But is there some handwavy
story you can tell about parallelization
where both transformers and TPUs are
about really internalizing the
importance of parallelization.
>> So I mean definitely um I put it
somewhat on people actually. Um so I
mean it is just true uh hardware is
massively parallel like you've got tens
of billions hundreds of billions of um
transistors on your chip and it takes
like maybe 100 clock cycles to get from
one side of the chip to the other and so
you can't like do a sequential
computation involving transistors on
both sides of the chip. So the hardware
is just fundamentally parallel and and
you have to uh take advantage of that.
TPU v1 and all later TPUs like naturally
took advantage of that. um just uh
matrix multiply is really nice because
it is so parallel. Um so I think on the
hardware side that's generally
understood.
>> I think most ML researchers especially
of the time um
were not sort of super deep in what
hardware wants and what is sort of
mechanical sympathy is some a term
that's used for that. Uh so I mean
>> sorry what is the term mechan I mean it
kind of
>> yeah speaks for itself. It's like uh I
mean I think about the poor machine and
and what does it want like uh
>> what does it want?
>> I mean the term actually I think
originates in maybe um uh high frequency
trading in areas like that which is I
haven't worked in. I've just like I I
like reading about the software that
people have built from there. Um and
it's like for them what does the machine
want? It wants a lot of instruction
level parallelism. This is CPUs not not
DPUs. wants a lot of uh um uh don't
don't branch like so uh unpredictable
branches uh kill your performance and so
think about the things that CPUs do and
how to use them best can I get to peak
performance on a CPU is sort of that
idea
>> I think the whole idea of peak
performance on a CPU is kind of crazy
like no one even says what is peak
performance what is my percentage of
peak on on a CPU because
>> performance of software running on CPUs
is really bad but on running on GPUs or
TPUs or AI chips ineneral general uh
actually that is the main focus is like
what is my percentage of peak can I get
70% or 80%.
>> Yeah. Okay. I feel like many people
listening to this know that uh GPUs
perform better for AI workloads than uh
CPUs. That's kind of a funny history
when you think about it where just uh
one day we woke up with all these very
mathematically intensive uh workloads.
first crypto mining uh and then AI. And
so then Nvidia is extremely well
positioned because they've been making
like GPUs for gamers that you would plug
into, you know, you'd buy your uh uh uh
Dell PC back in the day and maybe
upgrade the uh the graphics card by uh
plugging in a better Nvidia uh graphics
card than the one the uh the stock Dell
computer uh uh came with. And they were
incredibly well positioned to to capture
that. So I think people know that. What
is the intuitive explanation as to why
GPUs are better for AI workloads than
CPUs? Because I mean people say yeah
they're better for uh you know these um
mathematical computations but that's
kind of a total logical answer
basically. Is there some way you can
have a mental model for why that is the
case? Cuz I mean software instruction
sets also involve doing math.
>> Yeah. So I mean uh intuitions I'm not
sure. Let me try and just go to the to
the to the um some of the big
differences which is uh really wide
vector instructions is sort of the the
hallmark of a of a CP of a GPU. Um which
uh I think it's it's maybe if you want
sort of some intuition it's like uh how
much is spent on controlling the thing
and maybe control means like if I'm
driving a truck how much like is the
driver versus the payload. um a truck
has a huge payload in it that's more
like the GPU whereas um maybe a
motorcycle is more like the CPU where
you've got like the instruction like
actually just processing the
instructions um reading what do I have
to do next okay how do I do that um that
is most of the cost on a CPU whereas um
if you if you just keep the same
instructions but make the payload 100
times bigger then you can shift most of
the cost to be um in in the actual work
that you want to do.
>> Okay. Okay. So CPUs have been op
optimized for very complex instruction
sets whereas uh GPUs optimized for
>> yeah complex instruction sets and sort
of um
fine grained changing what you want to
do. So like I mean steering like in this
analogy like
>> a CPU can steer an obstacle course no
problem whereas like on a GPU you're
just going to go straight line for a
really long time.
>> Yes. Yes. Okay. So this is getting us
into um what is Matt X? uh how did you
guys started and which part of this
space are you attacking?
>> Yeah, so um Maddx is making uh the best
chips physically possible for LLMs. Um
[clears throat]
the where what led us into Maddx. Um so
Mike is the other founder. Uh Mike and I
were both working at Google. Um and we I
mean I was working on on the um
inference stack for for running LLMs and
I was uh saying like how can we make the
best software on TPUs for running um
LLMs. Uh and then what we really wanted
out of hardware was support much much
larger matrices. The mat matrices have
grown from maybe 128 in dimension into
the many thousands. Um and so like rock
goes to like
>> many trailers. Um uh so much larger
matrices and uh much lower precision
arithmetic um and we we you know we we
tried to move the TPUs in this
direction. Um TPUs have been moving in
this direction but they're are kind of
constrained by a lot of um other
workloads. There was a big ads workload
at the time. Um and so back in 22 before
chat GPT was released uh there was this
idea that LLMs were going to be a big
thing but um not conviction and really
hard to to make a big bet on that. Um I
think a startup is more of the right
place to make a big bet on a workload.
You either like if you fail it's fine
you just like another startup will
succeed. Um uh whereas
>> I think a company like Google or Nvidia
the next ship has to work for sure. Um
and and so
>> uh you can take more technical risks as
a startup.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Well, actually I would
say we we're taking sort of product
risks rather than technical risks. Yeah.
>> But is there actually product risk
because like it seems like LLMs are
going to work.
>> I I think now we understand it. Uh two
years ago or three years ago, I think it
was it was
>> and when you say the best chips for
LLMs, I mean I can think of multiple
ways to measure best. It could be best
performance per watt. It could be lowest
latency capable of handling the largest
models. What is best? In general, there
are two metrics which uh which LLM
workloads care about, which is uh
throughput, which is really just an
economics thing. Um I buy a chip for uh
$30,000 and then can I do 10,000 tokens
a second or 100,000 tokens per second of
of throughput? Uh that determines the
dollars per token. Um so throughput and
then latency. How fast how fast does the
thing respond? As I see the market, the
the economics seems to be most
important. Um,
ultimately, uh, the quality of the AI
you can train and serve is constrained
by I have only a $10 billion budget and
I and I want to train and serve the best
model I can on that budget. Um, and so
if you if I can have um more tokens per
dollar, then I can I can get a better
quality out. Um, so so we we are the
product we aim to build is far ahead on
on on latency on on throughput. Um but
then actually the sort of surprising
thing is we're um we're competitive with
the best on latency as well and and so I
think that is a unique thing in in
offering both in the same place
>> and is this for obviously in AI there's
training the models and then running the
models inference is this most
interesting for inference or is there
any training angle I mean incidentally
is it useful for training or but you're
trying to win inference is that how you
think about it I
>> I think that's a reasonable way to look
at it uh I think the best inference chip
today will be a train a really good
training chip as well. Um and so uh our
product is both training and inference
but um I think the first sales will be
an inference that's mostly just a market
effect where
>> it's easier to buy like it's not as big
of a risk to go to buy an inference
cluster than a as a training cluster.
>> I I think the product is really
compelling for training as well and so I
think it should be the best training
product.
>> Yeah. And you guys just raised a big new
round of financing.
>> Yeah. Yeah. That's right. So we um this
is a uh we've raised a series B round
it's led by Jane Street and and um
situational awareness uh situational
awareness that is Leopold Ashen
Brennan's fund he wrote the definitive
book on on on where a on agi and where
it's going um and then Jane Street
they're real technical experts they
understand all all the details really
well so very happy to be having them
lead the round um uh it is a uh it's a
$500 million round helps us um uh
actually ramp the manufacturing and
supply chain for for for for our chip so
we can bring our chip to market.
>> That's a lot of money.
>> Yeah, it is.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. No, I mean I think the like
roughly I would say it costs ballpark
$100 million to produce a chip in small
volumes. Um but then if you want to like
you see the orders that are going around
like uh Open AAI, Enthropic, Google are
going around buying multi- gigawatt
clusters. They cost like tens of
billions of dollars of of chips. um and
you want to deploy all of that in like
in a year or so. And so you just need a
massive supply chain uh behind you.
>> And so assuming everything works
technically, what uh what rate of
production could you start to see?
>> We have some estimates of where we'd
like to be on this. Uh this is um this
is I mean ramping to very large volumes
is is a huge challenge for anyone and so
obviously for the for the large players,
they've had some practice at it. Getting
to a very large volume for a startup is
hard. Yes.
>> Um we would like to be at a place where
we're shipping multiple gigawatts a
year.
>> Multiple gigawatts per year.
>> Speaking of the metrics, you know, you
talked about tokens per second. Um we
used to measure chips in flops and I
guess there some kind of custom flop
thing for um AI chips, but is everyone
just using tokens per second these days?
Is the industry aligning that on that as
the chip metric?
>> Yeah. So I mean I guess it's sort of
like an application metric versus uh um
the chip itself. Flops of the chip is is
is the key chip metric. Um uh there's a
little bit of like when you if I go and
say I've I've got a like an exoflop chip
to you um then sort of the appropriate
suspicion is to say okay but can I
actually use those flops effectively? Um
>> I see.
>> And so then you need to map the
application to that.
>> Yeah. So this kind of telling you the
usable um flops. Yeah. For for your
privacy. Okay. As a consumer of AI uh we
have known for a long time that lower
latency products succeed. Uh
Google talked about their internal
testing where the
>> differences were down to was it 50
milliseconds?
>> Something like that.
>> Yeah. Yeah. In result times where they
noticed more Google engagement the
faster the results were. And you'd think
that 50 milliseconds is imperceptible to
a human and it almost is but turns out
it's not. Uh and uh I think Amazon has I
mean certainly they've optimized the
latency of the Amazon experience quite a
lot. I don't know if they've talked
about this stuff uh publicly, but you
know that their internal metrics
similarly show that like the faster the
product page loads, the more people buy
it. And yet in AI, Google has carved out
a
meaningful
advantage
via Gemini just being really fast for
its level of intelligence and as far as
I can tell ahead of most of the other
labs at a latency at a fixed, you know,
high level of intelligence. Yeah.
>> Why have you guys or Gro or kind of
better chips not being adopted faster to
give this product latency? Is just that
like this will happen and you guys will
be powering all the uh AI products. But
I note that Google has a has an
interesting lead there.
>> I think there's ultimately like for at
least for existing chips in the market,
there's a really uncomfortable trade-off
between latency and throughput. The
chips that are best at throughput have
historically been the chips that are
based on HBM um as the as the memory. Um
so that is Google, Amazon, Nvidia.
>> Um uh in order to have very large
throughput, you need a lot of um uh a
lot of inferences in flight
simultaneously. Um so that needs the
large memory,
>> but that hasn't been so good at latency.
And then there's the Grock and Cerebras
that are are much better at latency
because they've got this uh the the
SRAMM weights are in SRAMM uh very low
latency. Um the problem is and the
challenge when you when you when you go
to a groba system is that the um the
throughput you get there it just is not
very good and so the um the fundamental
uh dollars per token is is is just not
competitive with with Google um or
Nvidia or Amazon. It is actually
possible to do both in the same chip. Um
you it's kind of an obvious thing. You
say you take the HPM you take the SRM
put them together in the same chip. You
put the the weights in SRAM and you put
the um the all of the uh inference data
in in HPM. Um that is what we are doing
in fact. Um and I think that actually
hits a really nice sweet spot where you
can get low latency and also be very
cheap. Um so I think that's a really
attractive point to be. It hasn't
happened in the market yet just because
of product decisions that have been made
by the different chips.
>> Got it. But we should expect it like we
should expect all the AIS we're using to
get significantly faster over the coming
3 to 5 years faster I would say.
>> Yeah. So, so I mean generally HBM based
chips tend to be about 10 milliseconds
or 20 millconds per
>> sorry HBM based chips are things like
TPUs.
>> That's right. That's right. Yeah. Um
there's yeah there's just some simple
math of like how long does it take you
to read through all of HPM takes about
20 millonds and so that's the amount of
time per token uh it runs whereas the
amount of time to read through all of
SRAMM is much faster and so you can
typically get about 1 millisecond. So
yes, be faster.
>> Famously, um software used to be like
old-fashioned deterministic software,
you know, the kind that's now out of
favor. Um used to be very um easy and
quick to scale and you know, you would
have social networks that have some by
Southwest moment and they can scale
through, you know, 10, 100, a thousand
orders of magnitude of, you know, adding
users because it's just, you know, a few
rows in the database and it's a very
underutilized uh CPU. What's interesting
about the AI world is there are very
real
uh bottlenecks. You know, you spend lots
of time talking about power, but it's
not just bringing power online. You
know, just you mentioning HBM is
reminding me of it seems like there's a
view that maybe there's some going to
be, you know, there's going to be some
HBM uh supply chain crunch. And so where
do you see are we in for just a crunched
world where some limiter is
[snorts] pacing the rate of AI buildout
uh over the coming few years where the
economics work of the products and
everything like that but ultimately we
just can't bring the components online
fast enough because we have to build out
the factories things like that and and
what are those crunched components?
>> Yeah. No, I mean I I I think so. And
I'll just comment by the way, this is a
great time to be a supplier in this
place. Um or or just really
>> You should have started an HBM.
>> I know, right? Like I think it's also
just a fun time to be someone who
optimizes software. Like I I always
that's always what I like doing. Uh
always the challenge is why am I
optimizing this if like if no one cares?
But finally there's a place where
actually like uh you can uh it's
actually very meaningful in a very
tangible sense like uh if I can make
this 20% more efficient then it can save
that 20% of of the buildout.
>> Um the supply chain uh we're going to
have crunches on on all of the supply
chain really. So um if you look at the
sort of the big components of what any
company but like us for example build
out um there is dependency on uh logic
dies from typically TSMC maybe Samsung
or HBM which are the big three HBM
vendors highinex uh Samsung and Micron
um and then and then there's also just
the whole rack manufacturing which
includes um
>> I mean literally just sheet metal and
and so on that that builds the rack but
also cables and connectors because
because of all the high speed
interconnect Um that's what we
>> Blackston sound hard. Are they sneaky
hard?
>> The the big challenge is that you want
to bring in a huge amount of power, get
a huge amount of heat out and also have
uh like phenomenal interconnect which
has very high signal integrity
requirements and so pack a lot of cables
in with uh the cables don't bend too
much. They have to have enough copper in
them and so on that you don't lose um uh
data rate on on the interconnect.
>> Yes. So, so, so yeah, if you push it to
a limited time, wafers, racks, HBM,
>> what else?
>> Data centers, which I think is is is
power primarily, um, a little bit of
buildout, but primarily power. Um, uh,
and and grid infrastructure there.
>> Okay. Um, how do you then as a startup
that is looking to acquire all these
components
>> elbow your way in amongst the giants of
the Googles and the NVIDIA and all these
people who are, you know, uh, have
longunning relationships and have been
buying for much longer.
>> Yeah. I mean, ultimately what they what
all of these suppliers care about, they
they do somewhat care about a diversity
of their own customers. It's it's not a
great position to be.
>> They don't want to monopony.
>> That's right. Yeah. Um uh but then you
know their their what is their
hesitation or the calculus for for one
of these large suppliers is um if I
reserve some some of my capacity for you
a startup um are you going to be around
in a year? Is anyone going to even buy
your product? Our approach has been to
um uh to just actually uh find buyers
for the product uh and then the the
buyers answer that question ultimately.
>> Got it. And so if you show up with a
bunch of fairly ironclad contracts to a
supplier then that that has helped.
>> That's the nature of it. Yeah.
>> I presume also the rand you just raised
really helps there where showing that
you are incredibly well capitalized and
not going anywhere also helps from a
supplier point of a supplier validation
point of view.
>> Yeah. Abs. Absolutely. Yeah. I mean it
it helps uh just to say that we are
around. We in some cases are actually um
it depends on which part of the supply
chain but some parts of the supply chain
um some some are fungeible uh logic D
are typically pretty funible uh but um
other parts of manufacturing are uh you
actually need something specifically set
up for you and so we we're also able to
cover the capital costs for that.
>> Yeah. Yep. That makes sense. And coming
back to the Matx architecture okay you
want to build the best problems.
>> What is that?
>> Yeah exactly. [laughter]
>> Um
>> sounds great.
>> Yeah. So I mean there's a few aspects to
that. I think the first one is just um
uh pick your memory system right. Um and
so I said like we've seen this HPM
family, we've got the SRM family. Put
them both together is actually I mean
most obvious idea but like you can
actually do it. Um uh there are a lot of
details to make that work well. Um we've
done that work. One of the things you
show that shows up there is you've spent
all of this area on your chip on on
SRAM. How do you fit in the matrix
multipliers which are the other big
thing you really need to do? um and so
somehow create a much more efficient uh
matrix multiply engine. There is a gold
standard for that that is called the
systolic array. Make a really large
systolic array. You can't beat that in
area or power efficiency
>> like provably. So
>> practically
>> practically it is not known a better
approach there. Um the main thing is
like where are the inefficiencies?
Typically the inefficiencies show up
when you leave the systolic array. So if
you make a really big if you make your
systolic array really big then um then
you just don't leave it as often. So
that's that's the idea. So make a really
big systolic array. That is sort of the
um the the theme of several of the uh
2023 era startups including us. Um but
uh one of the challenges there is now
there is this part of the neural network
as part of the transformer which is this
attention that doesn't map well onto a
large systolic array. And so that's
attention the the the the
mixture of expert layer maps really well
but the attention does not. Um and so
what we came up with which is quite
different than some of the other
startups in this space um is say take a
really large array but have a way to
split it up into pieces um without
losing efficiency. Um so sort of that is
the core of the of the design for us. Um
and then the sort of the third component
so first was HPM and SRAMM second is the
sister like ray third component is uh
just an an interesting new approach on
low precision arithmetic. um uh low
precision arithmetic. In general, we've
seen number formats get narrower and
narrower. Um they get faster and faster
as you make them um less precise.
>> Okay. Number formats get narrower. What
does that mean?
>> Yeah. So um float 32 um was how people
used to train uh neural nets.
>> And that's just too much precision. Like
it's
>> too much precision. Yeah. It's it's like
saying I've got a like uh I've got an
image with like uh a billion color bit
depth. It's like too many colors. Like
uh um you'd rather have more pixels and
fewer colors. So that trend seems to go
all the way like almost all the way down
to like one bit. Um where just have uh
have very few colors but a huge number
of pixels um and and that inn net seems
to be better um uh just more efficient
way to to train models. And so sorry
literally what um precision are you
dealing with in these? Uh
>> so um we have a range um the
uh
I mean we we actually have an ML team
who who we hired specifically to
research uh different forms of uh
numeric and how to make them all work
together really well. Um
we have a range of precisions. It's not
just one precision. We we think probably
the main thing will be uh similar to
where Nvidia is at which is four-bit
precision. Um but I think a mix of
different precisions is useful for just
when you look at the research sometimes
you want some layers in higher precision
or lower precision and so on.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Okay. So four bits is 16.
Yeah.
>> Yeah. You get 16 choices.
>> Yeah. That's it. Um yeah it's pretty
imprecise. Um
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Um that's really interesting. I didn't
know about that dynamic but it makes
sense.
>> Yeah. And half of them are positive,
half of them are negative. So like
>> it's even less.
>> Yeah. How do you design a chip? Like
what's is that a whiteboard? Like what
software are you working in? I just love
to know like I understand how you design
software and what that looks like. I
have actually no sense for what chip
design looks like.
>> So the the way that you actually type a
chip into a computer is similar to
software. So you write Verilog.
>> Um Verilog is a programming language. It
is a very parallel programming language
which makes it different than like C or
Python or or something. Um but it is uh
it is a programming language. So the
mechanics of how you express the design
are the same as software. Uh and we have
continuous integration, git, all of
those things.
>> But like a program executes like your
verilog program.
>> We don't really run it, right?
>> Yeah. Exactly. Like it. Yeah. Okay. So
so the so synopsis and cadence provide
EDA tools. Um they
>> So EDA you have to remember. Yeah.
>> Electronic design. [laughter]
>> I don't even know what it means really.
I think it's uh electronic design
automation.
It takes the the log and um and says
first turns it into a description of
what are the logic gates that are
involved and ors not and then the wires
between them.
>> Um and then it runs for days doing some
really difficult algorithms and then
eventually uh produces I mean so so so
gates are the first thing and then even
below that it literally just produces
polygons. It says like uh ptype
semiconductor here n type semiconductor
here um and and poly silicon. Yeah.
>> Okay. So like you write Verilog and then
that compiles down into Gates and
ultimately like the uh the Minecraft,
you know, 3D um uh just this is where
your your elements should go.
>> Um
>> but like
then what is the iteration loop? Like
when we write code at Stripe, we build a
first version of something and uh you
know then we try it out and then we uh
you know refine it and we add more
functionality over time. We're going to
write some tests at some point. We'll
ship that. We'll find product market fit
and then we'll refine it in market. Like
>> do you just sit down and write the
completed ship and it works really well?
>> Every year we tape out a chip and if
there's a bug we just wait till next
year. It's not really how we do it.
>> Yeah. So what's the how do we actually
do it? Yeah. Um it's much more waterfall
than soft. So like waterfall is almost a
bad word in software development. Um
>> which is a fact of life in Jupiter.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So um the waterfall goes
from architects to uh logic designers
who are writing verog. Um and then
there's this design verification and and
then physical design. Um so there's this
really big architecture phase which
happens before even writing any verog.
Um which is uh [clears throat] what do I
want the organization of my chip to be?
Um there's in some sense I mean what I
re like I came to hardware after doing
almost 10 years in software. I really
like the blank slate you get in hardware
and you've got like all of the raw
materials you have are much more um
varied in what you have available. Um so
what is the organization of your chip?
Do I have 100 cores? Do I have one core?
Um do I have systolic arrays? Do I have
vector units? All of those things.
And then we spend a lot long time coming
up with that general principle and then
saying okay now I've got these
applications I want to run I want to run
a transformer of a particular shape. I
want to map that uh onto this
architecture that I've got in my head.
Uh and so we do a lot of iteration. Well
I've got this architecture in my head. I
write it down to communicate to other
people but that's just like a markdown
file. Um uh and then and then still
actually a lot in my head but maybe with
Python simulation and so on. Um, I'll
see do my applications map well to it
and so can I can I run LLM?
>> This is where I was gonna go. Okay, so
you have a simulator where you write
your chip. You can then simulate its
performance and you have some battery of
tests that you kind of see how this chip
design works.
>> Is it like an industry standard,
you know, is it the XPlane of uh chip
testing?
>> Yeah. So I mean you
there's an industry standard thing for
the verilog once you've done the design.
Um they're just verilog simulators that
you can test against.
>> Okay.
>> Um
>> that is but you've already invested a
huge amount of work by the time you've
got to that point and so you sure hope
you haven't made a big mistake at that
point.
>> Yes.
>> Um so the thing that everyone does prior
to that is is uh we'll write our own
performance simulator. um which I mean
it is very specific to your particular
architecture and you can write it quite
concisely in in just like a normal
programming language and so uh that is
where most of the architecture work is
done and then the simulation on varog is
more I know what I'm doing I just want
to make sure I didn't have any bugs when
I implemented it
>> right but I presume it's a game of
inches where different people are trying
different things and then you uh do
simulate it to see if it runs 1% better
across the battery of tests or is that
not how it works
>> in this base not so much. Um, so I mean
just to sort of characterize what
performance of an AI chip is, it is how
many really like if you're just like
first thing you care about is flops. Um,
how many flops have I got? That's a
product of um, how many multiplies like
I've got a grid of a certain size like a
th00and by a th00and. So that's can do a
million multiplies in the clock cycle
and then I have a certain clock
frequency like a gigahertz and so I
multiply them out. That is the speed of
it. Um I don't even need to to write
that and test it to see how fast it is.
It
>> just is.
>> Um yeah. So like what I plan in advance
is it's going to be this fast. Um what I
can then optimize on maybe a little bit
is clock speed. There's not a lot I can
do there. Um and then I can optimize a
bit on area as well. So so there is some
room for optimization but actually a lot
of it gets set like the actually just
the speed of the chip gets set very much
up front.
>> Got it. And then how many chips do you
fab? Is it only the ones going into
production or is it just build a few to
throw away or how does it work?
>> Yeah, so um the ideal which uh companies
tend to hit about 50% of the time is
that uh your first tape out tape out
costs like $30 million. Um your first
>> tape out is just production money.
>> That's right. Uh it's the the actual
manual like the first chip costs $30
million. The second chip costs $1,000.
Uh so tape out is that is that first
chip. Yeah. Okay. The ideal is that your
first tape out is actually is your
production uh thing. So you you do a
tape out, you you make maybe a thousand
chips and test them and then you do
production volume.
>> Um in the unlucky 50% of the time you
need to redo some or all of your tape
out. So um in good cases and in many
cases you can redo just the metal layers
which costs you only like $100,000 um
>> as opposed to the pay the $30 million
again. Um uh but in bad cases like if if
you've made something serious and you
can't fix out the metal layers, you have
to do the whole thing again.
>> Why can't that be solved in like is that
definitionally an error in simulation
where it turns out these two gates were
close too close together and uh it just
led to some reliability issues or
>> Yeah. Um so yeah like what you're
describing is like physical like uh uh
the the physical implementation of the
chip is wrong. Uh that's one class. The
other class is that the logical
specification of the chip is wrong. Um
>> but shouldn't that be
>> shouldn't you have that before? Yeah.
>> Before you spend $30 million on
>> So I mean the yeah we do a lot of
testing. We try not to uh to ship these
things. Uh
>> I hear software companies also ship bugs
to production as well. And sometimes
[laughter] things sometimes things uh
>> there's a very good rhetoric. Shouldn't
you not be shipping bugs? [laughter]
Um uh but I mean like there is a real
trade-off in you can spend more and more
time on design verification. Yeah.
>> Um
>> uh like there's always this question of
when do you stop and like uh and so you
stop when your coverage metrics have hit
a certain point but like maybe not 100%.
Yeah.
>> And then if um you know Apple has to
discretise the iPhone release cycle and
they've settled on you know once per
year and so they'll decide you know
we've got this better camera but ah it's
got to wait for the next version. Uh or
you know we're going to improve the
waterproofing but you know that's got to
wait for the iPhone 8 or whatever. Uh
and so they have taken a continuous
process of like always coming up with
ways to make the iPhone better and
discretetized it into annual iPhone
releases. What will your discrete?
>> Yeah, many chip vendors have uh this
sort of tick- tock model which is um
you'll do on on one generation like
maybe you're trying to release every
year um on on even numbered years you'll
do a physical technology upgrade. So new
transistor technology, new memory
technology and new interconnect. Um and
then on oddnumbered years you might do a
architecture overhaul. I think that's a
pretty good fit because it um you have
different parts of that of your company
that are skilled at different areas and
it allows you to keep sort of both of
them occupied um without like having
instead every every two years doing a ma
massive risk release.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Okay. And so you think
that's probably likely for you?
>> Yeah, that's
>> um you mentioned interconnect. So
there's an nar out there that Nvidia a
huge part of the defensibility comes not
from the chips which are good but from
the uh software layer and the ability
for engineers to write these really
parallel workloads uh and the fact that
they've been refining CUDA for
>> whatever number exactly yeah a long time
just how do you think about
parallelization and is that narrative
true
>> yeah it's true for sure um it's true in
some in in many uh areas of the market.
Um I think
uh and especially where you look at
where Nvidia entered the market um
they're doing uh like uh PC devices uh
lots of gaming um and so on. There are
thousands of games maybe tens of
thousands of games released um and they
all need to be programmed against uh
against CUDA. And so um it's there's
such a huge investment in the software
that it that this is really important to
the compatibility. There are not
thousands of LLMs. There's one LLM per
frontier lab and there's maybe five
frontier labs or something like that.
Um, and so the just the economics of
that is different. The calculation for a
frontier lab roughly goes as I just
bought a $10 billion compute cluster.
Um, I have hired uh 50 of the best uh
people who can write um optimized uh GPU
or TPU or tranium software. um uh I pay
them less than $10 billion, a lot less
um and so um let's put them to to work
uh optimizing the the compute and so uh
they can like good work there can I mean
depends on what your baseline is but it
can very easily double the performance
of of of the software you write and so
there is a huge amount of custom
software written for every generation of
chip um when a new chip comes out uh the
software is uh like substantially
rewritten to optimize for that specific
chip and that's just the right trade-off
given the the relative costs of these
things. Um what that means for us is
that uh that that ecosystem already
exists. Uh and that way of operating
where you say I'm just going to staff a
50 person team to to run on uh to write
software for this chip um works really
well for if you're trying to sell to
Frontier Labs.
>> Okay. Okay. So, you're saying CUDA is
way more important for the games
environment where just there's a lot of
games. Yeah.
>> Than this topheavy AI market that we're
in where
>> if people say you need to
>> then customize your workload for a MATX
chip. It's like well fine custom
business.
>> Yeah. Yeah. That makes that makes a lot
of sense. Um
>> where will you fab the chips?
>> TSMC.
>> Okay. Yeah.
>> Um,
why is TSMC
so durable?
>> Yeah. I mean, it's interesting. They
don't charge a lot as well. You'd think
that if they're a monopoly provider,
they should charge a lot of money. Um,
they don't. Um, I think that is a big
aspect of why they're so durable. Uh,
>> it's like this cyclical, it's cyclical
conservatism crossed with Taiwanese
business conservatism means you're at
the like most conservative part of the
[laughter]
>> Yeah. Yeah, the matrix.
>> But but I mean it does uh I mean like an
American capitalist might say, well,
they're just they're just screwing up.
They they could have extracted more
money from the market, but you could
also say that um this is actually their
long-term sustaining advantage because
um uh they will just stay ahead for a
really long time.
>> They don't encourage the creation of
competitors.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. But isn't the creation of
competitors kind of priced in because of
geopolitical risk? And so like it's not
like everyone's fat, dumb, and happy
with their TSMC dependence. They're
actually thinking a lot about it.
>> Yeah. I mean, so there's real technical
advantage there as well. It's not it's
not just like the discouragement,
>> but like standing chips seems really
hard. Building airplanes seems really
hard. There are so many areas where
competitive market forces create
multiple options.
>> Yeah.
>> And yet that has not occurred here.
>> So I mean there are multiple options.
You can you can buy from Intel or
Samsung. Um
>> but at leading edge nodes.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So I mean what do we even
care about in leading edge nodes? I
guess the big advantage is on power. Um
the advantage on area is smaller. Um the
leading edge nodes the the density
doesn't go up as much as it used to. Um
so when you are really really sensitive
to power um it is a good idea to be on
leading edge nodes. So that is AI chips
and mobile phone chips.
>> Um but there are there's a lot of the
market where where you don't like
devices in Yeah. car chips. Yeah it's
fine. But but you're kind of saying like
if you exclude the two most interesting
parts of the market, you know, yeah,
[laughter] you
>> um just for for this super high growth
area of the market, it's interesting to
me like again there's a lot of other
>> really complex business problems out
there that competition has has solved.
Yeah, chip design is a like why has
someone not left TSMC and gone and built
a new fab?
>> Yeah, I mean I don't know. It's it's the
cost of a lab of of a fab is extremely
expensive. I mean, I recognize that also
the cost of a lab is extremely
[laughter] expensive, too. Um uh
>> I don't really understand the technical
details of why it's so hard. Um uh I
mean there is some amount of just a $10
billion fab versus a hundred million um
tape like tape out and and chip
development. There's a huge difference
there, but beyond that, I'm not sure.
>> What's JSMC like to deal with?
>> So, they're very big. So as a startup we
tend to work with um uh not directly
with CSMC but with a um an ASIC vendor
who who I mean firstly does a huge
amount of the actual backend work for us
that Jabase with them um but then also
has existing relationships with them.
>> Got it.
>> Um TSMC cares a lot about diversity of
their customer pool and so uh
>> and gets back to that conservatism.
>> Yeah. So we're they're great to work
with from from that perspective like
they they
>> they want to encourage startup.
>> That's right. That's right.
>> Yeah. That's very cool. Why don't the
labs design their own chips? I mean,
Google does, but
>> Google does. Um, Open AI is is starting.
It's really a trade-off of how much
advantage do you get from vertical
integration versus how much advantage do
you get by concentration of uh R&D work.
>> So, um, you take the five labs and if
they all buy from one player, then you
can put like five times as much R&D into
that chip. Um, and does that beat the
advantage you get from saying, "I know
exactly what my model is."
>> Because of the like several years delay
from from designing a chip to being in
production, um, you can't actually say I
know exactly what my model is because uh
models change like uh much faster than
that. So uh even the labs are forced
into this position where they have to
make predictions and they have to hedge
against what what they might do two
years from now. Yes. The calculus is
sort of like what is the probability
distribution of what my model might look
like and then sort of um design a chip
that gets like 90 90% of that
probability distribution or something.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Elon is excited about data
centers in space.
>> Yeah.
>> The two criticisms I've heard are that
cooling is very hard and then just
repairing
>> Yeah.
>> with chips is hard.
>> But I know nothing about chips.
>> You do?
>> Yeah. So I mean the repair I think is
really interesting. Um when you look at
how Nvidia deploys their ax, how we we
do something pretty similar to what
Nvidia does. Um I mean in general you
always need to design for the fact that
some of your chips are going to be down
like um uh meantime between failure of
chips is not that large. And so uh in a
cluster of 100,000 chips, there's going
to be chips that are down all the time.
>> Um one way you can do that is you can
make a rack with one where one rack has
um some spare chips in it. Nvidia has uh
eight spare chips and a rack of 64. Um
>> uh that's pretty good. Uh the like the
comedant RX works really well for you
there that the sort of uh you can
actually like because you can pick which
ones to avoid. You can um
>> uh you can like with very high
probability you tolerate a lot of
failures. And then the other just for
like the other family of things is to
say my rack has to work but I have some
spare racks as well. So you kind of you
can math that out with uh like a like
the tax of reliability here is only like
10%. It's pretty good. Um uh and and you
but that relies on someone coming and
servicing the part within a day or
something like that. If you say they're
going to service it never then um I
think you actually can get where you
want to be but maybe with 100% tax on
reliability rather than 10%. So, so for
example, if you think the average
lifetime of a chip is in the range of 3
to 5 years. Um, so that means if I
deploy twice as many chips, then 3 to 5
years from now, half of them will still
work.
>> Yeah. And also the burn-in is
particularly um failury. And how about
the cooling? So most of the challenge uh
I mean I I guess there's this there's
actually really a data center design
aspect uh that then um at the rack level
the challenge of cooling is just getting
the heat out like as quickly as possible
out of the rack into the um cooling
network. Um how you get it out of the
the the spaceship um other people would
know that better than I do.
>> Okay. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Um again that
seems to be the main objection but um
>> I don't know.
>> Yeah. I mean I I think it's sort of like
if you think the cost of repair is that
you need to have deployed twice as many
chips then like it's a trade-off of the
capital of the chips versus the power
saving.
>> Exactly. the repair thing it feels like
>> can be solved because also I think part
of the bet
>> you know probably's claim is that we
will just be so power limited that you
know you have no option but to go uh to
space and you know people can
argue about that but were that to be the
case then yes it's like well you can get
power in space and you cannot on earth
and so you uh you might as well go there
whereas like the cooling is a more
fundamental does the product actually
work yeah uh at
Rainer thinks about AI the unglamorous
way. Compute systems architecture and
what it takes to run models reliably at
scale. And if you're building an AI
product, the business model similarly
has a ton of unglamorous complexity.
You're not just selling AI, you're
monetizing consumption across API calls,
tokens processed, GPU hours. Stripe
billing is a scalable system for usage
based billing. It lets you launch
tokenbased pricing, subscriptions,
credits, hybrid models, whatever you
want. So you can create revenue models
based on usage without rebuilding your
pricing system every six months. If
you're building an AI product, Stripe
billing is worth a look.
What are your AI predictions for Twin26?
>> I mean, what I'm really excited about is
um just being able to I mean, I'm still
excited about the coding. Uh that's this
is what we do as a company. It's what
many others do as a company as well. Um
the uh one aspect of this is expanding
into more domains. Um so for example in
in where we spend our time um uh we as a
company we write rust we write veral log
we write python. Um
>> no hasll.
>> Yeah. No there's a story there. I I I I
used to love. I rust is my current
favorite. Mutation is good. Um uh um the
models are extremely good at Rust and
Python. Um they've done a lot of RL on
them. Um they have not done as much RL
RL on Verlog. Um they've done
>> almost none on okay write write me a
markdown file that describes a chip
architecture. Um and then how do you
even RL on that? You have to say like
>> uh what is a good chip architecture? I
have to say somehow say whether that's a
good result or not. Yes. Um I think one
of the things the labs are doing is
trying to broaden what they've done RL
RL on source it from customers and and
so on um in order to uh sort of fill out
the the the knots the make it less spiky
fill out the gaps between the spikes.
>> I presume the labs would love to work
with you on uh improving the models uh
by doing RL on this specific
>> uh task. However, it's also that makes
sense for us.
>> Yeah, you're a special sauce. So,
>> do you want to
come up with some AI approaches but keep
them proprietary? Is that
>> Yeah. So, I mean, we've looked at a few
different aspects here. There's the I
mean, what we're able to do by yourself,
we our business is not training models.
We we do it in order to do the research
on numericics, but like actual
production models we don't do. Um, so
it's like the biggest mileage I think is
on the RL and and it's not something we
can really do ourselves. We'd love it if
we could have a custom model just for
us, but uh that doesn't seem to be,
right?
>> The the terms we've been offered by labs
so far have not been on those terms, but
uh
>> because you have to share the IP back.
>> The way they prefer to do it is that
they that you um they [clears throat]
they put it into their mainstream model
because it's good for them.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Which obviously you
don't want to do. Um Yeah. I mean, how
do you think you what does you using AI
to design a model do you think look
like? Because this is actually, I think,
an interesting site glassass into the,
you know, a weak version of recursive
self-improvement where, you know, we're
using the AIs to develop better AIs. And
so, I'm curious, yeah. What what do you
what you think that looks like? Is it
your own proprietary um recursive
models? What what else? Like is there
kind of day-to-day AI usage that's
loadbearing?
>> Yeah. I mean so the the stuff that is
available today and I think uh will
become even better very quickly is just
um the stuff that looks most like
software. So writing varog running tests
running continuous integration and so
on.
>> Um
>> the uh and that is a big fraction of the
development time in a chip. It's
probably 9 12 15 months or so. Um the
there's some stuff that's downstream of
that which is physical design which is
uh you take that verilog and and you
generate the the gates and the polygons.
>> We don't have a clear path for like it's
not at least the most obvious thing is
not clear for how to how to compress
that like like the goal can you can you
tape out a chip in one month one month
would be the goal. Um in theory you
could compress all of the logic design
and design verification down to a short
amount of time if the uh just by
continuing on the same path we're doing
now. But if you wanted to take uh the
physical design down that has to leave
code. You're now doing like graphical
interfaces and saying I want to place
stuff and so on.
>> Yeah.
>> Actually there has been work on this
even prior to LLMs um uh which is like
specific um model trained for that
particular problem. Yeah. and and I
think the vendors um which is like
Synoptus and Cadence um probably will
should move in that direction. Um most
of the focus has not been do it faster.
It's being do it with higher quality.
>> Um
>> uh but that is a big bottleneck on on
like can I have a new chip every month
and then there's just the practical
thing of like a new chip every month
doesn't really make sense because then
if I'm deploying
>> uh like if it takes me a year to
populate a data center that means I'm
going to have different chips in
different corners of the data center.
>> Yes. Yes. Sorry, when you talk about one
month to tape out. Yeah.
>> So you do all this work to ultimately
produce a file.
Uh everything TSMC then does it's not
entirely in software like is there some
type setting that has to happen of
moving stuff around but yeah what
happens when you you send your file to
TSMC?
>> Yeah.
>> Then what?
>> So they create a mask. So that is uh
where the ASML tools come in. Mh.
>> Um,
and a mask is it is really just a
stencil. You shoot the the lasers
through the mask and or the X-rays
through the mask and and then that um
that uh produces the different PT type
and N type semiconductors. Um so they
produce the mask that is the expensive
part. Um and then uh and then they're
they're building up these like 15 or so
metal layers. So they they place on the
silicon and then there are different
layers of metals um which connect all
the transistors together. Um uh they do
that on a wafer. It it it happens on on
a on a stepping basis. Uh so there's
sort of a maximum size of chip you can
build which is constrained by this
machinery.
>> Um
>> the wafer stepper is part of the ASML
special sauce, right?
>> Yeah. I guess there's probably some
important alignment requirement there.
>> Yeah, I think I remember that being
quite like the you know it's a classic
manufacturing throughput problem and I
think they've done a lot of work on
optimizing that.
>> Yeah. Um so so they take that. So then
you just produce hundreds of copies of
of your chip. Um you have to test it
because there's defects. Uh you
typically I think the average rates um
really depends on process and and so on.
But small single-digit number of defects
per per chip. Um so you test the chip
and see whether it has any defects in
it. Um many chips are designed to be
able to tolerate a few defects. Um and
so you need to configure it to tolerate
the defects. Um, and now you have a die
that by itself works. Uh, and then you
need to package it. So you put it on uh
in a package together with uh memories.
Typically that's the HPM. Um, and then
and maybe uh some you escape the wires
to to connect to other chips.
>> How long does it take to make a mask?
>> Um the so I mean what we see is time
from like tape out to to first chip to
chips back. Uh again depends on node but
it's buck four or five months. Oh, so
tape out is just uh like sending the
file or
>> Yeah, I mean we consider tape out as
send the file and then and then there's
a whole process of you make the masks
for all the layers and then and then uh
actually just producing the chips.
>> Got it. So producing the masks and
producing the chips happens after tape
out.
>> That's right.
>> I see. Okay. So like is the term tape
out from like you send a magnetic tape
with the instructions or something?
>> It could be. I was in software when when
when created what the tape actually
means.
>> It feels like,
>> you know, we're thinking about AI
predictions. One thing I'm really struck
by is how uh
still in 2026,
>> every time you open a
>> chat window, it's contextless. It's got
no memory. And now to be fair, it's
like, guys, it's been four years. Like,
just not even four years. It's been
three and a half years. Just calm down.
We'll get there. But I also interpret a
lot of the current enthusiasm for open
claw and all that stuff as it's like
this super hacky backdoor into state
management where you know your little
claw will write a markdown file of what
it's doing and then you know look at
that markdown file the next time and
things like that. But it just feels like
state management and memory is going to
be a huge deal and that will really
change the character of AI products.
>> Yeah, it's really interesting like the
the so I mean long context is the reason
is one of the biggest bottlenecks on
model perform on speed of the model.
Yes. Um it just need like every single
token you generate it reads through all
of the previous tokens or maybe it reads
through a subset of them but reads
through a lot of the previous tokens
you've written. Um and so memory
bandwidth for that is is is really
constraining. You can think of like
model level ways to solve that problem
which is to say um maybe I can compress
it in just fewer bytes or something like
that. Uh but it's interesting that the
sort of most effective way to solve it
has been I mean it's really a
combination of everything but the most
effective way to solve it has been uh
once you hit your 300,000 token limit uh
have the model go back through it and
compact and and uh
>> I mean that's kind of what openclaw is
doing. It's like everything you've done.
Yeah. Um but it's funny that
>> it's so manual.
>> Yeah. I mean I think uh
>> manual is the wrong word. I mean it's so
primitive.
>> It's maybe because it's so controllable.
Um you can like uh if you want to
iterate on how you compact, you you give
a different prompt and you say compact
this way, compact that way, you can
iterate that on that in in seconds or
minutes. Um whereas if you're trying to
do some iteration on the model where you
say now I' got a different model
architecture it's going to take like
months to and launch something.
>> Yes. Yes. Any other AI predictions?
>> I'm generally just interested in what
makes models cheaper and faster. Um so
that's uh just at the model architecture
level really tied into this context
thing. I think the context size will
stay ballpark the same where it is maybe
a few times larger. Um but the parameter
count will go up like parameter count
should grow much much faster than than
context length actually just because of
the the underlying physics of of what's
available
>> though
has that been the story like would that
be a reaceleration of parameter count
because it feels like we've leveled off
slightly in the last year or two and
instead we've been focusing on more and
better RL.
>> Yeah. Okay. uh parameter count or token
thinking tokens I guess those those are
are available but the context length uh
I think is is sort of struggling to
grow.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Okay. But you think we
>> you say context length is struggling to
grow but you're saying we keep context
the same length.
>> Keep context the same length
>> but we're better at working with large
context. Is that what you're saying?
Because
>> uh yeah I mean just have um application
level interventions to to manage large
context like compacting.
>> Yeah. Yeah. cuz I think everyone's had
the experience, you know, currently of
like the chat conversation and the
further down in the chat you get,
>> it just gets looser and sloppy. It's
just like really sloppy by the end and
it's like making mistakes or whatever.
So, you're saying we start to do better
with with large contacts. Okay, I buy
that. When will I be typing into a chat
window and it is a Matax chip underneath
it powering it?
>> Kad in under a year. Um, and then that
means uh chips available in sort of and
yeah. Okay, that's exciting. Okay, so in
2027 I will be seeing very high
performing chats as a result of uh
>> in the 1% experiment of the users or
something like that.
>> Yeah, exactly. Yeah, I did find a way to
finagle myself into the uh the AB test.
Yeah. Um MaddX is 100 people.
>> That's right. Yeah.
>> How have you gone about building the the
team, the culture?
>> Yeah. So I mean so what we have on the
team is hardware mostly hardware um but
a big software team and also a big ML
team.
>> Uh I think the ML team is quite unusual
in in what we ask them to do. When you
look at a typical ML team in a uh AI
chip company it will be um what I might
say ML engineering or ML performance um
they're writing kernels that uh that
actually
will just like use your hardware as well
on on a given model. There's sort of a
missed opportunity there if you're
saying uh all we do is we take other
people's models and we write kernels for
them. Uh you're you're optimizing this
but you can optimize this at the same
time. And so we want to optimize the
whole thing at the same time. So like
real code design.
>> Yeah.
>> So our ML team is actual real ML
research. Uh what they do every day is
they train um small LMS uh um from
scratch focusing on numeric um and and
and attention. Um and this has really
really helped us uh make a like an
interesting product. Um it's showed up
most strongly in our numeric. Um
>> we
often what you see when people design
numeric is they say well back in when
when flow 32 was popular it would be I'm
going to follow the le e standard. Now
it is like follow the open compute
standard. Um uh and there's lots of
little details where you say things like
um maybe what's the rounding mode I'm
going to use like round to nearest even
or something like that which is like uh
the the the best known standard for how
to round. We want to cut corners
anywhere we can. Um and so like maybe
don't do the best rounding, maybe don't
do uh the uh like don't get all the
corner cases correctly. Um that's a very
scary proposition if you're just making
those choices blind, but if you have the
benefit of a research team who can sort
of uh back you up as you do that. Um it
it it's really powerful and it's really
interesting that we can make some uh
sloppy choices in these cases.
>> I feel like often technical advances
come through better iteration loops. Um
a favorite example of this I found
recently was that the Wright brothers
actually had a failed season before
first flight. So I guess first flight
was 1904 and they were down in Kittyhawk
in 1903 and not making that much
progress. and they went back and they uh
to Ohio and they had a wind tunnel and
they were like testing their design in
the wind tunnel. You can imagine not a
lot of wind tunnels in uh in 1904 um and
they did a lot of wind tunnel testing
and their successful flight was uh was
after that. Is this something you're
focused on where you know to get better
chips you allow for a better testing and
iteration loop and what does that look
like?
>> Yeah. Uh I think this mostly happens in
the architecture and uh product
definition stage. Uh maybe even more
generally I think uh AI chips seem to
live or die by product definition and
architecture. Um
>> what is the most extreme form of fast
iteration is doing it in your head. Um
and so can you map a model to hardware
in your head? Can you estimate the
performance of what it is uh in your
head? Um you're not going to be 100%
perfect, but maybe you can prove some
kind of lower bound on performance. Um
and so uh the I mean the simplest
possible thing is my model has uh a
trillion parameters. My uh device can do
can can do a billion multiplies per
second. So it takes a thousand seconds
to run or something like that. Um just
do that simple division. Um but then
there are much more complicated things
like we tend to look at uh resource
balances and so like how many memory
fetches do I need to do per multiply or
something like that. So we do um uh I
mean at least the way I like to do uh
design and architecture and and uh and
optimization is to be able to sort of
estimate the performance to within about
30 40%.
>> Um
>> before even typing anything in at all.
Um and so we've tried to do that a lot.
>> Um
>> uh a lot of our architecture comes from
there.
>> Um then sort of the next stage of
iteration is oh that's kind of on the
performance side. This also happens on
the um on the circuit design side as
well. Can you take a circuit and say
what is the gate count on that? So like
a uh a 16- bit multiplier has
approximately 16 squared many gates. Um
and you can do that for more complicated
things by like sorting networks and so
on. So we already have a pretty good
idea of the costs and speeds of things
at that point after doing these
calculations. Um then what we tend to do
as as sort of the next step of iteration
is uh on the ML side we run model
experiments. you get iteration speed
just by having small models mostly.
>> Um and then um uh on the hardware side,
we uh we use simulators, performance
simulators to like do the next level of
detail to to make sure we're we're
seeing all the things we want to see.
>> Yeah. Yeah. This um idea that you should
the best iteration is in your head. Uh
it's kind of reminding me of Jeff
Dean's, you know, numbers every like do
you have your equivalent of that numbers
every MATX? So yeah, we have go/gates in
our company which says what is the cost
of an exor gate, an ANDgate, a full
adder, um SRAM, bitsell and so on
>> and you want people to be working with
that stuff in their head and have an
intuitive sense for it because again
leads to better um
>> iteration. What is the pitch to someone
joining Matx?
I mean I think if you are someone who
likes optimizing just
>> optimize something
>> software hardware uh factorial uh
whatever um
>> if you're trying to like fit something
into the smallest budget possible I
think is a pretty exciting place to be
>> um
>> uh I think hardware place hardware
companies in general are really exciting
because you have such a broad range of
skills of people on the team. you have
software people, you have hardware
people, you've got physical design,
you've got people who are just like
looking at the insertion force of a rack
into of a card into a rack. Um, and so
there's like so much discussion and
learning you can do. Um, I think Maddox
in particular, um, we we really care
about this and I think we extended all
the way up into the application and the
machine learning as well. And so uh um
uh really I mean uh really really really
interesting tactical problems and uh and
I think just generally um like there's
lots of interesting people to talk to.
>> Yes. And presumably in terms of impact
if you can design a meaningfully higher
throughput chip a 20% higher throughput
chip means 20% more AI is happening. you
know, if the bottleneck is elsewhere
like um you know, power or something
like that or cost um you actually just
are
>> meaningfully increasing the amount of
intelligence in the uh in the world
which is presumably exciting to people.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I mean I think uh this
shows up both as just uh can it apply in
more applications as well as just how
smart is the model?
>> Yes. Yes.
>> Why rest? So a previous project I worked
on at Google um we did a lot of HA
hasll. Um I I did Haskell growing uh
[snorts] like uh when I was at school uh
I loved it like very uh principled, very
interesting. I like Haskell but I also
like making stuff fast. And then the
question is uh what is the first thing
you want to do? You want to be able to
modify your memory. Hasll you jump
through hoops to do that. Uh maybe I
just want a language that is like
programming like functional programming
that lets me modify my memory. Um so I
think uh Rust has a lot of the nice
things which are like uh type classes or
traits um uh and and a and a rich type
system. Um one of the things that we we
have done um like interesting ways we
use it at MaddX are the the range of
sort of data types that you express on
software like what are the integer types
uh int 32 in 64 int 8 maybe that's all
you care about. Um but it turns out in
hardware you you like you care about
every single bit and so you you you want
to use like 17 18 19 bit integers. um
the that that is quite natural to
express um and we've built up sort of a
whole ecosystem of of of um rich
hardware data types in in Rust as well.
>> Has Rust beaten Go for the position of
sort of performant type programming
language with modern features or do they
actually address different? Yeah. I
mean, so there's like there's the
there's what the Rust marketing will
say, which is uh um
>> uh safe without a garbage collection. Um
which I think is a is a real um I mean
is the objective thing that you can say
is different, but sort of Barry is the
lead which is is also just like it's got
nice type system features that that that
Go doesn't have.
>> And then like why is garbage collection
why does it matter at all? like it's not
I mean people often focus on the time it
takes to run a garbage collector but the
the other thing is that every time you
allocate an object you've got the object
and then you've got the garbage
collector header at the beginning and so
it uses a lot more memory as well and so
if you want to design some I don't know
data structure that like uses the right
amount of memory rather than like a bit
more than
>> oh sorry so I hadn't realized that in
Rust you're allocating your memory
manually versus in go you have a right I
didn't realize that okay and you prefer
that for what you're doing or just is
>> I just really like dealing with the
details like you give me a puzzle and
I'll be like let me solve every single
piece of it and so so uh that tickles
that part of my mind.
>> It seems like you're a fan of
optimization generally. Is that a fair
characterization?
>> Yeah.
>> Where else have you So chip optimization
is one um domain. Where else?
>> Yeah. So I mean I started um I mean uh
when one of the really exciting things I
I found about working at Google is like
the whole Google codebase is available
and you can look at
>> how does a memory allocator work, how
does a mutx work, how does a hashmap
work, any of those things and you can go
and look inside the implementations and
Google has like excellent
implementations of those like the some
of the best you could uh you could you
could write. Um uh so like one of the
things I did on my nights and weekends
uh when I was at Google was just um go
find those implementations uh write a
benchmark. How many nanoseconds does it
take to allocate eight bytes of memory?
Um and then can I make that faster? Can
I uh maybe I inline this function? Maybe
I look at the assembly and say looks
like like there's a few memory moves
here or there's some registers that are
are being used that I don't need in the
in the fast path. I only need in the
slow path. can I can I do something
there? Um, so I don't know that was
always my uh like just fun and learning
activity. Being outside of Google, uh I
feel I mean I probably could have done
this inside of Google as well, but
outside of Google I felt the luxury to
be to be able to like talk about uh
these results as well. One of the things
I've looked at recently is um just
hashts are used so much. Um uh one
prompt for me was like what would uh if
I wanted to design like custom CPU
instructions for accelerating hash
tables like hash tables are one of the
most common things I'm looking at them
up and and writing them all the time.
What would the optimal CPU be for that?
Um and so then well then the follow
following down that chain is like uh
what are the um what is the best hasht
implementation in the first place? And
so so I spent some time looking at um
different SIMD implementations and
there's this really cool technique
called cuckoo hashing where you hash
into two different locations and then
you uh you uh you use the bucket which
is less full.
>> Um
uh it's been in the literature for
decades. Um and yet like the best hasht
implementations don't use it because
it's somehow uh like not practical. And
so
>> as why is it not practical? practical
hashts are uh these days considered to
be ones that use um uh SIMD vector
instructions um to to scan like eight
buckets at a time. Um
uh and the way cuckoo hashing is
normally described is I look up one
bucket here and one bucket there and so
I'm not using the vector instructions.
Vector instructions are much faster than
scalar instructions and so there's kind
of a missed opportunity. Um again just
like take the two good ideas and stick
them together. do vector instructions on
cook hashing um is uh you have to be
careful to get the details right but if
you get it right you it can actually
just win
>> and soar is your claim that one could
design a custom CPU that has way better
hasht performance or even on current
chips you could get way better hasht
performance
>> um so so both uh I mean I I'm interested
in what you can design in custom
hardware but Maddx doesn't make CPUs
we're not going to make CPUs and so
>> new line of business
>> I it we we just want to focus on
shipping one product well um for for the
time being.
>> Good answer.
>> So I mean I think it's an interesting
exercise but I I don't get to feel the
like the endorphins of of seeing the
number going down. So so I I I first did
this on just Intel CPUs and and you can
you can get better performance um than
like some of the best hasht
implementations um available um using
cuckoo hashing on Intel CPUs even. M and
what are examples of workloads that are
really um hasht read intensive? I mean I
know kind of everything but
>> uh I mean JavaScript I guess but uh um
>> yeah I mean it's sort of a tricky
exercise because like when you really
think about it you're like did I really
need a hash table there? I probably
didn't but you just reach for it all the
time.
>> Okay but you could go to the you know
Google JavaScript team and probably help
them eek out better performance in the
Chrome JavaScript engine. Yeah, I mean
potentially like it's I mean I'm not
going to spend my time on this.
>> Well, if they're listening to this
podcast, here's a free idea
>> from RER and then explain the dragon.
>> Yeah, this is from a book that when I
was working on the Jax team. So, the Jax
team is one of the ML infrastructure
teams at Google. I I was there as the
most recent team before I left. Um
>> and sorry, what does Jack the Jax team
do?
>> Oh, yeah. So, the Jax team develops uh
this is sort of Google's new more modern
version of TensorFlow or um competitive
PyTorch. uh it's it's how you write
models in Python uh to run on TPUs. A
big part of the JAX team however is to
say okay we have Jax the technical
artifact um can we uh help enable users
to actually use it really well and get
high performance.
>> Mhm. And so ultimately that became well
who are the users it's people writing
LLMs. How do you get good performance on
LLM? Um and so really really strong team
um the Jack team at Google although as
with a lot of brain people are now
elsewhere as well. And so we developed a
lot of the different techniques for how
to lay out models efficiently on on many
chips. And so uh ultimately some some
people at Google and and I contributed
after I left Google wrote this uh guide
called how to scale your model. How to
how to run an LLM as fast as possible.
Um, it is sort of the main reference for
how to get high performance on TPUs.
There is now also a GPU version of this
as well. It's a dragon because it's how
to train your dragon.
>> I see. Okay. Um, last question. Uh, you
know, people might not have thought that
uh there's room for new chip companies.
It might have seemed unusual or very
hard. Uh, and you guys, it seems like a
very good approach with um with that.
Where do you think are other
opportunities for companies to be
started uh here in 2026? Where do you
think people should be looking for
entrepreneurial opportunities or just
technical challenges that haven't been
properly addressed?
>> More labs I think is still interesting
like the just can we do more on model
architecture is always interesting. Um
>> you think we have not fully explored
model architecture space? Yeah, I mean
the the Frontier Labs have done a pretty
good job of exploring it, but I think I
mean uh there's uh as the hardware
changes the the the shape of the model
should change for sure.
>> Yeah. Okay. And presumably you're not
thinking like yet another Frontier Lab
pursuing the same architecture. You
think there's probably off-the-wall
looking architectures that will actually
make a lot of
>> Yeah, I think there's a little bit off
the wall.
>> Okay, for sure.
>> Yeah. Do you have a specific
architecture in mind? My mentality is
always sticking within the transformer
family but or like what are the um what
are the constraints that are currently
available like currently imposed that
you could you could uh you could lift.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Um so for example one of the things is
there's this idea um when you're doing
transform inference you do prefill that
is sort of processing what the user said
to you and then there's decode which is
generating the response to that and
those are totally different uh in in
pretty much every aspect of how um how
they actually run. um one runs a step at
a time, the other one runs really in
parallel. So there is this somewhat
artificial constraint today that those
are the same model that's doing both. Um
maybe lift that constraint. Um another
example would be there's this idea that
the model that you uh I mean this is
this is more fundamental constraint that
you have to train the same model as you
serve. Um but again training is very
different from serving. Um at training
it's very compute intensive at serving
it's more memory bandwidth intensive.
And so maybe is there a way you can make
a model that when you use it in at
inference time it um it increases the
amount of compute it does to to use some
of the available resources.
>> Yeah, makes sense. Well, runner. Thank
you.
>> Pleasure.